Finding Aid for Office of Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs (University of Michigan) records 1981-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs (University of Michigan) records 1981-1997
University of Michigan. Office of Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs.
University of Michigan office established to meet the academic and social needs of the university's minority students. Records include administrative files; materials relating to various programs and activities; and topical files. The topical files include extensive information on the yearly Hispanic Heritage Celebrations.
997 Bimu 2
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Office of Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs in August 1998. (Donor no. 8752 ). Additions made by Denise L. White (Donor no. 11371 ) in 2015.
The collection is open for research.
In 1977, the Office of Minority Student Services (MSS) was created by the University of Michigan in order to help meet the academic and social needs of its minority students. MSS added to its campus programming by establishing a new division to handle the diverse student population. The Office of Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs was set up in 1983, as a campus and community environment for minority and multi-ethnic students to succeed. Supporting the students through a variety of academic, social, economic and personal counseling services, as well as coordinating student cultural and multi-cultural organizations and programs were the goals of this office.
The Office of Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs functioned as a non-elected representative organization for minority students for University of Michigan programs. These representatives were hired for their experience in working with students of diverse cultures and backgrounds. The staff included but were not limited to: Asian American, Native American, African American, Indian, and Hispanic/Latino/a.
The first Hispanic representative, Rosa Lopez, served from 1983 to 1988. Lopez was succeeded by Katalin Berdy from 1988 to 1997. The Hispanic representative was responsible for sponsoring student organizations, programs and activities within the university. For the organizations, the Hispanic/Latino/a representative served as a staff advisor, working with the students and helping them reach their social and academic goals. The student initiated organizations were comprised of both academically and socially motivated programs. Some of these organizations included the Socially Active Latino Students Association, (S.A.L.S.A.), the Hispanic Business Students Organization, the Council of Hispanics for Higher Education, Alianza, Puerto Rican Association, Sigma Lambda Beta Fraternity, Inc., Sigma Lambda Gamma Sorority, Inc., and the Latino/a Network. The Latino/a Network (L Net) served as an elected body for all the other Hispanic/Latino/a groups on campus. As a governing board, L Net contained two representatives, either voted for or appointed, from all the other organizations and made decisions on planning what university activities, especially the Hispanic Heritage Celebration, would occur.
The Hispanic/Latino/a representative also acted as a liaison to the larger, Michigan minority business and government community, and social action organizations. This included involvement with the United Farm Workers Support Group, New Detroit, Inc., and LA SED, Inc., (Latin Americans for Social and Economic Development). These community organizations helped students protest the serving of California grapes in university dining halls (because of poor working conditions and treatment of the United Farm Workers and other minority farm workers who pick the grapes), motivate campus leaders into action, and provide opportunities and work experience for student volunteers within their organizations. Many local governments, businesses, and organizations aided in support for the annual Hispanic Heritage Celebration, which originated as a national festival in the early 1980's.
In 1981, the Professional Improvement Program (PIP) was launched in collaboration with Dr. Harold Fowler and Deborah Orr May of the Office Career Planning and Placement and Eunice Royster, former director of academic services and Comprehensive Studies Program. Funded by Dow Chemical Company and Xerox Corporation, this program was designed for minority students interested in pursuing careers in business and industry.
PIP served two primary purposes. Program leaders hoped to create student ambassadors to guide and provide membership for incoming and transfer students. They also envisioned the program to aid in matriculation success of minority students through varied workshops and experiential opportunities offered through major corporations, civic and governmental agencies, and campus professionals.
During its brief history, many noteworthy individuals visited the program to share their wisdom including tennis legend Arthur Ashe and Thomas Moore, head of the Sterling Automotive Group Foundation. The program ceased operation in the late 1980s.
The records of the Office of Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs consist of files on administration, student and community organizations, programs and activities and topics such as student information relating to the Hispanic representative. The Hispanic Heritage Celebration is well documented in these records.
Subjects:
Hispanic American college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Career Planning and Placement.; University of Michigan. Office of Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs.; University of Michigan--Students.
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative series includes office correspondence, financial files, meeting minutes, and planning proposals, giving information on the daily operations of the Office of Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs. The Administrative series includes records of Minority Student Services (MSS). Within these files are notes from the MSS retreat, MSS training council, and the multi-cultural training program. These programs helped the staff learn more about other cultures and how to plan better programs that serve the needs of students who identified with those cultures.
  - Correspondence
    - Within University of Michigan
      - 1985, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
      - 1992-1996 (Box 1)
    - With students 1989-1992 (Box 1)
    - Outside University of Michigan 1989-1996 (Box 1)
  - Financial Records 1987-1994, 1997 (Box 1)
  - General Information 1989-1994, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Leadership Retreats and Conferences 1989-1995 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes 1988-1994 (Box 1)
  - Minority Student Services
    - Minority Affairs Commission 1989 (Box 1)
    - Minority Student Services Retreat 1990-1993 (Box 1)
    - Multi-Cultural Training Program 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Student Information 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Student Services Programming Council 1983, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Reports 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Surveys, Studies, and Polls 1989-1996 (Box 1)
- Organizations, Programs, and Activities
  The series Organizations, Programs, and Activities is comprised of files on community organizations, University of Michigan units and organizations, and University of Michigan student organizations, and events sponsored by both community and university organizations. The community organizations are those which are part of the Ann Arbor and/or Michigan community but not affiliated with the university. These include the United Farm Workers Support Group, LA SED (Latin Americans for Social and Economic Development), and New Detroit, Inc. The University of Michigan units and organizations are those affiliated with the university, but not necessarily limited to just students and not student initiated or run. Within this file are: Center for Education of Women (CEW), Hispanic Leadership Development Program Alumni Association (HLDPAA), and Professional Improvement Program (PIP). The University of Michigan Student Organizations are those groups which are part of the university and run by students with advisors from the Office of Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs, and include both social and academic groups. Included in these files is information on the Chicano Graduate Students Association, the Puerto Rican Association, Socially Active Latino Students Association (S.A.L.S.A.), Alianza, the Hispanic Business Students Association, the Hispanic Law Students Association, and Sigma Lambda Beta Fraternity, Inc., and Sigma Lambda Gamma Sorority, Inc.
  - Community Concerns 1985-1996 (Box 1)
  - Community Organizations
    - Congress of the U.S. Congressional Hispanic Caucus 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Instituto de Cultura Hispana Americano, Inc. 1990 (Box 1)
    - LASED (Latin Americans for Social and Economic Development, Inc.) 1983, 1988-1992 (Box 1)
    - New Detroit, Inc. 1985 (Box 1)
    - United Farm Workers Support Group 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - Events
    - General Information 1983, 1986-1994, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Events
    - Chicano History Week 1990-1991, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Latin American Week 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Native American History Month 1997 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Organizations
    - Center for the Education of Women (CEW) 1991 (Box 2)
    - Hispanic Leadership Development Program Alumni Association (HLDPAA) 1987-1989 (Box 2)
    - Projects, Proposals and Planning 1987, 1991-1993, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Coalition for Democracy in Latin America 1987 (Box 2)
    - Professional Improvement Program, 1981-1988 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Student Organizations
    - Basic Information 1988-1994 (Box 2)
    - Alianza 1989-1994 (Box 2)
    - Chicano Graduate Student Association 1986 (Box 2)
    - Council of Hispanics for Higher Education (CHHE) 1987 (Box 2)
    - Delta Tau Lambda Sorority 1994 (Box 2)
    - Hispanic Alumni Association 1986, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Hispanic Business Students Association 1991 (Box 2)
    - Hispanic Law Students Association 1985-1987 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical File series consists of two subseries, Student Information Files and the Hispanic Heritage Celebration. The Student Information Files have materials on how this office helped students, with loans, recommendations into graduate programs, attaining scholarships and advise for course of action in case of discrimination. The Hispanic Heritage Celebration subseries is arranged by date, beginning in 1983 when the festival began. Records for each year include information on events and activities, as well as correspondence, planning proposals and meeting minutes detailing all the work that goes into planning this city-wide month-long celebration.
  - Student Information Files
    - Educational Concerns 1988-1990, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Educational Concerns 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Emergency Student Loans 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - General Information for Students 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Scholarships, Programs, and Award Information 1991-1995 (Box 2)
    - Student IMPACT (Interdisciplinary Multicultural Project for Academic Community Ties) 1993 (Box 2)
    - Student Recommendations 1992-1995 (Box 2)
  - Hispanic Heritage Celebration
    - 1983
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Events (Box 2)
      - Financial Records (Box 2)
      - Planning, Proposals, and Meeting Minutes (Box 2)
    - 1987
      - Events-Planning (Box 2)
      - Financial Records (Box 2)
    - 1988
      - Events-Publicity (Box 2)
    - 1989
      - Budgets, Plans, Notes, and Meeting Minutes (Box 2)
      - Correspondence
        - Events (Box 2)
        - Planning (Box 2)
        - Publicity (Box 2)
      - Reports (Box 2)
    - 1990
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Events-Speakers and Lectures (Box 3)
      - Financial records (Box 3)
      - Planning Proposals, Notes, and Meeting Minutes (Box 3)
      - Reports (Box 3)
    - 1991
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Events
        - Film Series (Box 3)
        - Planning (Box 3)
        - Publicity (Box 3)
        - Speakers and Lectures (Box 3)
      - Planning, Proposals, Notes, and Meeting Minutes (Box 3)
      - Reports (Box 3)
    - 1992
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Events-Publicity (Box 3)
      - Financial Records (Box 3)
      - Planning and Proposals (Box 3)
      - Reports and Recommendations (Box 3)
    - 1993
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Events
        - Art Exhibit (Box 3)
        - Publicity (Box 3)
      - Financial Records (Box 3)
      - Planning, Proposals, Notes, and Meeting Minutes (Box 3)
      - Reports and Recommendations (Box 3)
    - 1997
      - Events List (Box 3)